<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
PHP-XMLRPC Extras User manual
$Id: xmlrpc_php_extras.xml,v 1.7 2007/03/06 10:45:10 ggiunta Exp $
-->
<book lang="en">
  <title>EXTRAS packages for the PHP-XMLRPC library</title>

  <subtitle>version 0.5</subtitle>

  <bookinfo>
    <date>25 February 2007</date>

    <author>
      <surname>Gaetano Giunta</surname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2006, 2007 G. Giunta</year>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>All rights reserved.</para>

      <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
      modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
      met:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Redistributions of source code must retain the above
            copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following
            disclaimer.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
            copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following
            disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials provided
            with the distribution.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Neither the name of the "XML-RPC for PHP" nor the names of
            its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
            derived from this software without specific prior written
            permission.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND
      CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING,
      BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
      FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
      REGENTS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
      SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED
      TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR
      PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF
      LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
      NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS
      SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This collection of utilities provides many additional features to
    the PHP classes that are part of the PHP-XMLRPC library.</para>

    <para>Altough very useful for specific purposes, these files have been
    omitted from the base distribution in order to keep it small and
    focused.</para>

    <para><ulink url="???">PHP-XMLRPC</ulink> is a php library which
    implements the XMLRPC protocol.</para>

    <para>XMLRPC is a format devised by <ulink
    url="http://www.userland.com/">Userland Software</ulink> for achieving
    remote procedure call via XML using HTTP as the transport. XML-RPC has its
    own web site, <ulink
    url="http://www.xmlrpc.com/">www.xmlrpc.com</ulink></para>

    <para>Support for JSON and JSONRPC is part of this distribution.</para>

    <para><ulink url="???">JSON</ulink> is a format devised to ease
    serialization and deserialization of common data types without incurring
    the overhead that is normally associated with XML. It is a subset of the
    Javascript language, and as such it is easily manipulated within web
    browsers.</para>

    <para><ulink url="http://www.jsonrpc.org">JSONRPC</ulink> is a remote
    procedure call protocol that uses HTTP for transport and a json syntax
    extremely similar to the xmlrpc one.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new</title>

    <section>
      <title>rev. 0.5</title>

      <para>This is the first release of the library to only support PHP 5.
      The corresponding version of the base library is 3.0.0 beta</para>

      <para>Quite a few changes and bugfixes have been made in the are of json
      support:</para>

      <para>improved: catch exceptions thrown during execution of php
      functions exposed as methods by the jsonrpc server</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>improved: catch exceptions thrown during execution of php
          functions exposed as methods by the jsonrpc server</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>fixed: fix bad encoding if same object is encoded twice using
          php_jsonrpc_encode</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>improved: json_extension_api.php: added json_last_error()
          function and the constants defined in php 5.3.0</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>improved: allow 'mixed type' jsonrpc servers (see description
          in the xmlrpc server docs)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>improved: allow 'phpvals' jsonrpc servers to do type checking
          on incoming requests</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>fixed: a missing 'new' call when building string vals in
          php_jsonrpc_encode</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>fixed: encoding of UTF8 chars outside of the BMP</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>fixed: encoding of '/' chars in jsonrpc when source is in
          UTF8</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>rev. 0.4</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>DOCXMLRPCS got a bugfix for php installs where
            magic_quotes_gpc is set and an option to take advantage of a
            visual editor for xmlrpc values (the editor being part of the
            jsxmlrpc package, it has to be downloaded separately)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the usual lot of bugfixes for JSONRPC: slightly faster
            handling of data which is internally encoded as UTF-8; support for
            booleans, strings, null as valid id in requests and responses;
            correctly add quotes when serializing datetimes; correct handling
            of charset declaration in http headers; switched the declared
            content-type from 'text/plain' to 'application/json' as per the
            proposed rfc; modified json_extension_api.inc to follow php
            445/521 semantics</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>added in AJAXMLRPC a new server class that takes advantage
            of ths jsxmlrpc lib for the generated javascript code (instead of
            jsolait)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>one bugfix in XMLRPC_EXTENSION_API</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>rev. 0.3</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>This manual was, albeit in complete, added to the
            distribution</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a new php file has been included in the JsonRPC package,
            which implements the same API as the PHP native JSON extension: it
            can be used to replace the extension in those situations where
            modifications to the application server are not feasible, such as
            websites on shared hosting etc...</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>bugfixes in the JsonRPC and ADODB packages</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>rev. 0.2</title>

      <para>See the <filename>NEWS</filename> file for a detailed list of
      changes in release 0.2</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>System requirements</title>

    <para>The PHP-XMLRPC library base package, version 2.1 or later, is a
    prerequisite for the extras packages.</para>

    <para>A working php setup is of course needed.</para>

    <para>The base library is tested to work with php versions ranging from
    4.0.5 to 5.2. Please note that not all library features are available for
    every PHP version. The "curl" php extension is needed to support https
    calls. The "json" and "xmlrpc" php extensions do not interfere with the
    operations of either the base library or extras.</para>

    <para>A complete testsuite has not yet been implemented for every
    component that is part of the extras. This prevents complete regression
    tests to be carried out against all php versions. If you encounter any
    quirk, especially with old php installs, please report it on the <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/phpxmlrpc">project development
    pages</ulink>.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>List of packages in the distribution</title>

    <para>The 'extras' library is formed by many separate components, grouped
    together for ease of download. The terms 'component' and package' are used
    interchangeably within this manual to indicate groups of files that
    provide a particular capability. Please note that the term 'package' is
    used with a different meaning on the library download pages on the
    www.sourceforge.net website, where the complete extras collection is in
    fact called a package in itself.</para>

    <para>Included packages as of the current release are:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>ADODB: designed to provide a flexible and easy-to-use
          database-to-webservice conversion mechanism. Based on the <ulink
          url="http://adodb.sourceforge.net">adodb</ulink> library by John
          Lim, it includes conversion functions, server component and
          meta-db-driver that allows transparent access to remote databases
          over http.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>AJAX: demo of an ajaxified version of the php-xmlrpc lib:
          supports executing xmlrpc/jsonrpc calls directly from the client
          browser. Needs the excellent jsolait lib from <ulink
          url="http://jsolait.net/">http://jsolait.net/</ulink> (thanks Jan
          Kollhof) or the jsxmlrpc lib.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DOCXMLRPCS: subclass of xmlrpc server that auto-generates HTML
          documentation of exposed services. Easy as a breeze to use, and
          extremely user-friendly (it is used on the main php-xmlrpc website,
          too).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JSONRPC: support for this brand new protocol, 100%
          buzzword-compliant and ajax-ready. Client and server classes
          provided. Makes it very easy to build a server that supports both
          xmlrpc and jsonrpc protocols at the same time. The original JSON
          parsing code was from Michal Migurski (whose lib is now officially
          part of PEAR).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>PROXY: subclass of xmlrpc server that can act as remote
          (transparent) xmlrpc proxy to forward calls to a remote server. Can
          either forward any received call or probe the remote server first
          for existing methods.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>WSDL: the completely UNOFFICIAL DTD and RELAX NG schemas to
          validate your xmlrpc against. Might be useful in defining some wsdl
          file describing xmlrpc services (good luck!!!). The DTD is not quite
          accurate, due to inherent limitations in the definition language.
          The RELAX NG schema should be on the other hand 100% precise and
          accurate.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XMLRPC_EXTENSION_API: a replacement for the php native xmlrpc
          extension, written in 100% pure php. Typical use case: enabling a
          php application, written taking advantage of the php native xmlrpc
          extension, to run also on webservers where the extension is not /
          can not be installed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>ADODB package</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>The main purpose of this package is to provide a flexible and
      easy-to-use database-to-webservice conversion mechanism. In layman
      terms, we want to provide an easy mean of connecting applications to
      remote databases using a web service protocol instead of a native
      database driver.</para>

      <para>Current features include:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>written in 100% PHP, runs on Windows, Linux and many
            variants of UNIX</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>use of ADODB as database backend enables connection to a
            great number of different databases (even LDAP!)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>uses XML over HTTP as data transportation layer: can be
            deployed in different setups and will work across proxies,
            firewalls etc...</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>provides a SOAP inbterface as well as an XMLRPC one</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>uses standard web-service protocols with libraries available
            in many programming languages, allowing coders to write new
            clients for integration within existing platforms</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>includes a generic SQL-to-HTTP proxy that can be used to
            build two or three-tier application architectures eliminating the
            need for installation of database connectivity on clients</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>can be used to save money on database licensing costs</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>if properly coded, clients can become 100% database platform
            agnostic, i.e. you could switch databases with zero impact on
            clients and limited impact on the middle-tier</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>many, many times slower than accessing databases using
            native driver interfaces</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>does not take advantage of many particular programming
            features of advanced databases</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>files</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>client_driver_examples.php</filename>: php demo
            code showcasing usage of this package to connect to remote
            databases via the xmlrpc ADODB driver</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>client_examples.php</filename>: php demo code
            showcasing usage of this package to connect to remote databases
            via xmlrpc</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>readme.txt</filename>: a short description of the
            purpose of this package</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>schema.svg</filename>: a graphical representation
            of the typical deployment scenario</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>drivers/adodb-soap.inc</filename>,
            <filename>drivers/adodb-xmlrpc.inc</filename>: adodb database
            driver files, to be used together with the server components for
            transparent db access</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>lib/tosoap.inc</filename>,
            <filename>lib/toxmlrpc.inc</filename>: the files containing the
            core conversion routines</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>server/server.php</filename>,
            <filename>server/server_config.inc</filename>,
            <filename>server/server_functions.inc</filename>: the server
            component: it receives incoming xmlrpc calls and maps them to
            database operations. Server.php is the webservice endpoint, while
            server_config.inc is the con figuration file that has to be
            tailored for every installation</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Usage</title>

      <para>This distribution consists of 3 main modules:<orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>an adodb-recordset to xmlrpc-value (and viceversa)
            conversion module for adodb, forming the core of the
            library</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>an xmlrpc web-service server that provides the functionality
            of a SQL-to-HTTP proxy</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>an xmlrpc driver for ADODB that can be used to transparently
            connect applications to remote databases using the xmlrpc
            web-service server</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>Module 1 can be used stand-alone in any application;
      module 2 depends on module 1 and module 3 depends on both 1 and
      2.</para>

      <para><graphic fileref="../adodb/schema.gif" format="GIF" /></para>

      <para>The above schema documents a typical usage scenario. We will refer
      to that image throughout the rest of the documentation.<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>part A is the database to be accessed by the client app. It
            can be any database supported by adodb</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>part B is the PHP-powered web service that lets remote
            clients access the database using xmlrpc function calls. It needs
            a php-supporting web server to run</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>part C is the client application, and is the most varying of
            the 3 parts:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>it can be written in PHP and make use of the adodb
                  xmlrpc driver (module 3 above). The programmer only needs to
                  know the adodb api.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>it can be written in PHP and make direct use of xmlrpc
                  calls. The programmer needs to know the phpxmlrpc api and
                  decode 'by hand' the recordset received from the db</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>it can be written in any other language than PHP,
                  making use of an appropriate xmlrpc library</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>it can be part of a website as well as a stand-alone
                  application</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>Needless to say, all 3 parts can reside on the same as
      well as on 3 completely separate physical servers (any combination is
      allowed).</para>

      <para>A few usage cases:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A is SQLserver, B is IIS. They both reside on the same
            Windows 200 server. C is a PHP application running in Apache on
            Linux. Advantage: no need of ODBC drivers on the linux
            server</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A is Sybase, B is Apache. They both reside on the same
            Solaris server. C is is a PHP application running as a service on
            a SCO Unix. Advantage: no need for recent Sybase client libraries
            when compiling PHP on SCO</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A is Oracle, B is Netscape Fasttrack. They reside on
            different servers in the intranet. C is a PHP application running
            in Apache on a hardened Solaris in the DMZ. Advantage: instead of
            giving direct access to the internal database through the firewall
            separating the intranet and DMZ networks, only a (custom) port is
            opened for HTTP request</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Installation</title>

      <para>Server side (tier B of schema)<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>unpack the php xmlrpc lib and put it into a directory where
            it can be included by php scripts (see directive include in
            php.ini). NB: only the two files xmlrpc.inc and xmlrpcs.inc a re
            actually needed. NNB: to avoid potential security problems
            possibly put them in a directory outside of the web server
            root!</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>unpack the adodb lib and put it into a directory where it
            can be included by php scripts NNB: to avoid potential security
            problems possibly put it in a directory outside of the web server
            root!</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>unpack in a temp dir the contents of this distribution,
            then<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>copy toxmlrpc.inc.php in the main adodb dir</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>copy adodb-xmlrpc.inc.php in ADODB/drivers</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>choose a directory inside the web server root where
                  the web service will be active. Copy in there the files
                  server.php, server_config.inc.php and
                  server_functions.inc.php</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>edit the configuration of the web service: edit the file
            server_config.inc.php</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Client side (tier C of schema)<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>unpack the php xmlrpc lib and put it into a directory where
            it can be included by php scripts (see directive include in
            php.ini). NB: only the two files xmlrpc.inc and xmlrpcs.inc a re
            actually needed. NNB: to avoid potential security problems
            possibly put them in a directory outside of the web server
            root!</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>unpack the adodb lib and put it into a directory where it
            can be included by php scripts NNB: to avoid potential security
            problems possibly put it in a directory outside of the web server
            root!</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>unpack in a temp dir the contents of this distribution,
            then<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>copy toxmlrpc.inc.php in the main adodb dir</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>copy adodb-xmlrpc.inc.php in ADODB/drivers</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>API documentation</title>

      <para>To be documented...</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>SOAP version</title>

      <para>To be documented... suffice to say that we provide a wsdl file and
      a nusoap-based implementation, too</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Road map</title>

      <para>Add support in the SQL-to-XMLRPC proxy for the missing 90%
      functionality of adodb, such as sql bind parameters; create a
      stand-alone web-service server making use of a continuously running php
      script (e.g. nanoweb or pear::http) instead of using an external web
      server; benchmark for speed / bandwidth; see all todo items in the
      code</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Ajax package</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>files</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>axjaxdemo.php</filename>: demo file showcasing
            construction of a complete ajax client/server solution in a single
            php file, based on xmlrpc and jsolait</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>ajaxdemo2.php</filename>: demo file showcasing
            construction of a complete ajax client/server solution in a single
            php file, based on xmlrpc and jsxmlrpc</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>ajaxmlrpc.inc</filename>: file containing core
            logic to wrap xmlrpc function calls and exposed methods into js
            objects</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename><filename>sonofajax.php</filename></filename>:
            demo file showcasing construction of a complete ajax client/server
            solution in a single php file, based on jsonrpc</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>usage</title>

      <para>To be documented...</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>DocXmlRpc package</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>files</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>docxmlrpcs.inc</filename>: contains the class
            extending <classname>xmlrpc_server</classname> with the capability
            to generate html documentation of exposed methods</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>docxmlrpcs.css</filename>: the stylesheet used by
            defalt by the self-generated html documentation</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>usage</title>

      <para>The purpose of this package is to let users have human-readable
      documentation automatically generated for all xmlrpc methods that are
      implemented by a given xmlrpc server.</para>

      <para>The documentation produced will be in HTML format, and it will
      exactly match the information that the xmlrpc_server class makes
      available to clients via usage of the
      <methodname>system.methodHelp</methodname>,
      <methodname>system.methodSignature</methodname> and
      <methodname>system.listMethods</methodname> xmlrpc calls. As an extra
      feature, documentation for single parameters of xmlrpc methods can be
      added. Html forms will be included with every method synopsis
      description page, to help the developer do quick'n'dirty
      debugging.</para>

      <para>The simplest way to make usage of the extra capabilities of this
      package is to take an existing xmlrpc_server and swap the php class used
      with <classname>documenting_xmlrpc_server</classname>:<programlisting>// define the dispatch map describing all of the xmlrpc methods exposed by this server and the php functions that implement them
$dmap = array(
  '' =&gt; array(),
  ...
);

// include the php code implementing the xmlrpc methods
...

// build the server and let it do its job: that's it!
$server = new documenting_xmlrpc_server($dmap);</programlisting></para>

      <para>Since version 0.4, the html forms that are generated by the server
      class can take advantage of the javascript-based visual xmlrpc value
      editor that is part of the jsxmlrpc library (downloadable as a separate
      package from the sourceforge.net project pages), making it even easier
      to invoke the implemented webservices via a browser interface. This
      optional feature can be enabled by setting the
      <varname>editorpath</varname> member of the server:</para>

      <para><programlisting>$s = new documenting_xmlrpc_server($dmap, false);
$s-&gt;editorpath = '../javascript/'; // enable link to js visual editor of content: set this to the directory where it is located
$s-&gt;setdebug(3); // enable maximum debugging level, just in case
$s-&gt;service();</programlisting></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>JsonRPC package</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>files</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>jsonrpc.inc</filename>: contains the classes
            implementing the JSONRPC client and the JSON encoding/decoding
            functionality. <function>include()</function> this and
            <filename>xmlrpc.inc</filename> in your PHP files to use the
            classes</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>jsonrpcs.inc</filename>: contains the JSONRPC
            server class. <function>include()</function> this in addition to
            <filename>xmlrpc.inc</filename>, <filename>xmlrpcs.inc</filename>
            and <filename>jsonrpc.inc</filename> to get server
            functionality</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>json_extension_api.php</filename>: contains the
            functions that emulate the php JSON extension API.
            <function>include()</function> this in addition to
            <filename>xmlrpc.inc</filename> and
            <filename>jsonrpc.inc</filename> in your PHP files to have access
            to the required functionality</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>server.php</filename>:</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>benchmark.php</filename>:</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>testsuite.php</filename>: testsuite used to verify
            adherence of this implementation to the native JSON
            extension</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>JSONRPC functionality</title>

      <para>The API is basically the same as the PHP-XMLRPC base library: all
      the classes have "jsonrpc" instead of "xmlrpc" in their names, but
      method names and members do not vary.</para>

      <para>To be documented...</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Native JSON extension emulation layer</title>

      <para>The <filename>json_extension_api.php</filename> file has been
      created with the goal of letting developers write applications taking
      advantage of the functionality offered by the php JSON extension, and
      allow them to deploy on php installations where that extension is not
      /cannot be installed. Since the reimplementation is written in 100% php,
      it can be deployed on virtually any php setup by simply copying three
      php files. The API of the native library is reproduced feature for
      feature and bug for bug, with the following exceptions:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>when trying to <function>json_encode()</function> a php
            string value that contains characters outside of the UTF-8
            encoding range, this implementation will return a json string
            containing different characters from the ones intended (a.k.a.
            garbage), while the native extension discards invalid characters
            and any following. Please note that if you are trying to do this
            your code is most probably wrong.<programlisting>var_dump(json_encode("Günter, Elène"));

// this implenentation
string(19) ""Gnter, El\u8ba5ne""

// native extension
string(3) ""G""</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>when calling <function>json_encode()</function> on a php
            float value, the json representation generated by this
            implementation will always contain a fractional part, whereas the
            native extension does not. This feature allow us, when using this
            implementation to both encode and decode, to distinguish between
            int and float values and rebuild them with the correct php type,
            despite the JSON protocol lacks two separate types.<programlisting
            lang="php">var_dump(json_encode(1.0);

// this implementation
string(3) "1.0"

// native extension
string(1) "1"</programlisting></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>An interesting feature of this implementation, not offered by the
      native implementation, is that it allows to transparently encode/decode
      php strings to/from json using the ISO-8859-1 character set for the php
      representation, instead of UTF-8. ISO-8859-1 is the native character set
      of php, so this is the behaviour that is most likely to best fit the
      majority of usages.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>API documentation</title>

        <para>Please note that if you <function>include()</function> the
        <filename>json_extension_api.php</filename> file on a php installation
        where the native JSON extension is loaded, the functions provided by
        this implementation will be automatically renamed to
        <function>json_alt_encode</function> and
        <function>json_alt_decode</function>. This prevents function name
        clashes and makes it easy to compare the output of the two
        implementations.</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>json_encode</title>

          <para>Encode a php value into a JSON formatted string.</para>

          <para>See the description in the php manual for more details.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>json_decode</title>

          <para>Decode a a JSON formatted string into the corresponding php
          value(s). Returns NULL on error.</para>

          <para>See the description in the php manual for more details.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>$xmlrpc_internalencoding</title>

          <para>The character set to which the JSON strings will be converted
          by <methodname>json_decode()</methodname>. Defaults to "UTF-8" for
          compatibility with the php json extension, but can be set to
          "ISO-8859-1" or "ASCII".</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>$json_extension_api_120_behaviour</title>

          <para>The behaviour of the php json extension was changed in between
          versions. Up to version 1.2.0, calling
          <methodname>json_decode()</methodname> on strings representing
          scalar json values (ie. strings, booleans, numbers and null) not
          encapsulated within an array or struct would return false. From
          version 1.2.1 onwards, decoding single scalar json values is
          allowed. By setting the value of the global variable
          <varname>$json_extension_api_120_behaviour</varname> to true or
          false, the behaviour of the emulation layer will be altered to
          follow the different versions of the extension.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Proxy package</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>files</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>proxyserver.php</filename>: demo of a simple
            xmlrpc service acting as proxy to the webservices of
            phpxmlrpc.sf.net</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>proxyxmlrpc.inc</filename>: xmlrpc proxy server
            class definition</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>usage</title>

      <para>To be documented...</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>WSDL package</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>files</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>xmlrpc.xsd</filename>: a XML Schema Definition
            attempting to describe XMLRPC</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>xmlrpc.wsdl</filename>: a XML Schema Definition
            attempting to describe XMLRPC method calls and responses</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>schema.rng</filename>: a RELAX NG schema
            definition describing XMLRPC (using xml notation)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>schema.rnc</filename>: the same RELAX NG schema
            definition describing XMLRPC (using ... notation)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>rationale</title>

      <para>The XMLRPC protocol has been specified a long time ago, at the
      dawn of XML and is described only in natural language. Attempts have
      been made to "reverse specify" it with DTD or XSD, with little success.
      Both definition languages are in fact too limited in their capability of
      expressing valid xml constructs to capture in a complete and correct
      fashion the XMLRPC semantics (see
      http://www.cafeconleche.org/books/xmljava/chapters/ch02s05.html for more
      details. Suffice to say that XSD does not allow to specify two
      consecutive xml elements with the same name but of different types, such
      as the faultCode and faultReason response members happen to be).</para>

      <para>The RELAX-NG definition language on the other hand has been found
      capable enough to fully describe XMLRPC, and the schema that is part of
      this distribution can be used to validate any XMLRPC request or response
      conforming to the spec. IT IS NOT AUTHORITATIVE because the XMLRPC
      specification is copyright by Dave Winer, and he seems to have lost
      interest in any further development of the protocol, but it should be
      considered accurate and production ready (if you find any bugs, please
      let the authors know, using the <ulink url="???">project's web
      site</ulink>).</para>

      <para>This situation is very unfortunate, since WSDL has emerged as a
      widely accepted web services standard, and a plethora of tools exist to
      parse existing WSDL files and automatically generate code stubs or
      generate WSDL definitions from existing code. If a WSDL representation
      of XMLRPC webservices could be generated, the net result would be
      greatly inreased interoperability between SOAP clients and toolkits and
      XMLRPC server implementations.</para>

      <para>Even though the apparent goal of the WSDL language design was to
      allow description of every possible message exchange, using every
      conceivable xml serialization over any transport (and a lot of the
      redundancy, verbosity and complication of the language are direct
      consequence of the flexibility sought), existing implementations de
      facto only support the SOAP binding for webservices, and XSD as language
      definition schema. RELAX-NG, while nominally accepted, has yet to find
      widespread usage in webservices toolkits. This leaves us with
      almost-bot-not-quite interoperable solutions.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>XMLRPC extension API package</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>files</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><filename>xmlrpc_extension_api.inc</filename>: contains the
            classes and functions that emulate the php XMLRPC extension API.
            <function>include()</function> this in your PHP files to have
            access to the required functionality</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><filename>testsuite.php</filename>: testsuite used to verify
            adherence of this implementation to the native extension</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>usage</title>

      <para>To be documented...</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>API documentation</title>

      <para>Please note that if you <function>include()</function> the
      <filename>xmlrpc_extension_api.php</filename> file on a php installation
      where the native XMLRPC extension is loaded, the functions provided by
      this implementation will be automatically renamed to
      <function>xmlrpc_alt_encode</function>,
      <function>xmlrpc_alt_decode</function>, etc. This prevents function name
      clashes and makes it easy to compare the output of the two
      implementations.</para>

      <para>To be documented... suffice to say that you can read the
      documentation for the php xmlrpc extension on the php manual.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
</book>
